A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices xFA116
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Field Offices - New Delhi, India, 1960-1978, undated; 7; 4.4 Cubic Feet 11 document cases
  Research and postgraduate training were viewed as interrelated activities. In 1958, with the Foundation's support, a postgraduate school was inaugurated at the Indian Agricultural Research Institute, New Delhi (est. 1905), with the authority to award the M.Sc. and Ph.D. degrees. After 1960, new legislation made possible the creation of several state agricultural universities modeled after American land-grant universities. These universities developed relationships with the various crop improvement programs and offered valuable research opportunities for American and Indian agronomists.
  The All India Coordinated Cereal Improvement Projects, the backbone of the IAP research program, represented a new approach to crop research in India. Sponsored by the Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR) and jointly operated by the ICAR and state institutions, each project studies the agronomy, entomology, pathology, genetics, and breeding of an individual crop. For the first time, research stations and substations were established throughout the subcontinent in order to coordinate research activities across the major agro-climatic zones. The programs began with maize in 1957 (although maize work had begun in India in 1945) and came to include sorghum and other millets (1957), wheat (1961), and rice (1965). Notable increases occurred in wheat production with the importation in 1965 of dwarf materials from Mexico. In conducting seed development research, the IAP benefited from the expertise of those RF agronomists who had served first in Mexico, namely Edwin J. Wellhausen, Ulysses J. Grant, Ernest W. Sprague, and the 1970 Nobel Prize winner, Norman E. Borlaug. Allied areas of research included drainage, fertility, soil and water management, and agricultural economics.
  In 1973, the RF decided to bring to a close its Indian Agricultural Program. India continued to carry out crop improvement work, utilizing the administrative, teaching, and research structures jointly established over seventeen years by the IAP and the Government of India. The RF therefore phased out its involvement in all improvement programs except rice, which was continued until 1975 by Wayne H. Freeman at Hyderabad. From 1976 to 1983, the Hyderabad office under Leland R. House operated the International Crops Research Institute for the Semi-Arid Tropics (ICRISAT). This institute functioned as part of the Foundation's "Conquest of Hunger" program, which had been formally established in 1963.
  In October 1964, Chadbourne Gilpatric took up residence in India as Visiting Professor in Philosophy at Delhi University, with responsibilities for representing RF interests in the Humanities and Social Sciences (HSS). Under HSS director Joseph E. Black (1964-70), Gilpatric sought to advance research and teaching in the humanities and in the social and hard sciences. He was particularly eager to strengthen curriculum at agricultural universities and to increase and preserve library holdings. From 1968 to 1972, Gilpatric coordinated a socioeconomic study of small farmers in Uttar Pradesh state. Gilpatric returned to the United States in April 1972. The Social Sciences programs had been officially phased out in 1970 and replaced with separate Arts and Humanities divisions.
  The New Delhi Field Office records (RG 6.7) of the Rockefeller Foundation Archives document the operation of the office and the programs it administered in the medical, agricultural, and social sciences. The records span the dates 1935-76, but ninety percent of the record group dates from the period 1956-73 and relates to the Indian Agricultural Program (IAP), operated by the RF's Natural Sciences and Agriculture Division. The IAP records provide a comprehensive account of the RF's role in establishing an international collaborative program of technical assistance. They also constitute an important source for the study of the history of modern agriculture and agricultural education in India.
  Important Subjects
  Agricultural education--India --Agricultural experiment stations--India --Agricultural innovation--India --Agriculture and state--India --Agriculture--Asia --Agriculture--India --Green Revolution --High Yielding Varieties Programs --Indian Council of Agricultural Research (New Delhi) --Indian Agricultural Research Institute (New Delhi) --International Rice Research Institute (Philippines) --Plant introduction--India --Virology--Research--India --New Delhi--Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations --Rockefeller Foundation--India --Rockefeller Foundation--Division of Natural Sciences and Agriculture--Indian --United States Agency for International Development
  Important Names
  Allen, LeRoy R. --Anderson, Richmond K. --Baird, Guy B. --Balfour, Marshall C. --Barnard, Chester Irving --Borlaug, Norman Ernest --Bugher, John C. --Corwin, J.D. --Cummings, Ralph Waldo --Douglas, Johnson E. --Fosdick, Raymond Blaine --Freeman, Wayne H. --Gilpatric, Chadbourne --Grant, Ulysses J. --Gregg, Lucien A. --Harrar, Jacob George --House, Leland Ralph --Joshi, A. B. --Kerr, J. Austin --Mason, Max --Morison, Robert S. --Moseman, Albert H. --Pal, Benjamin Peary --Parker, Dorothy --Rachie, Kenneth O. --Rusk, Dean --Sprague, Ernest W. --Stakman, Elvin Charles --Starnes, Ordway --Strode, George K. --Swaminathan, S. --Warren, Andrew J. --Weaver, Warren --Weir, John --Wellhausen, Edwin J. --Work, Telford H. --Wortman, Sterling
  Rockefeller Foundation Presidents
  Max Mason, 1929-36 Raymond B. Fosdick, 1936-48 Chester I. Barnard, 1948-51 Dean Rusk, 1951-61 J. George Harrar, 1961-72 John H. Knowles, 1972-79
  Medical Program
  Foundation Representatives in New Delhi W.P. Jaycocks, 1935-42 Marshall C. Balfour, 1942-46, 1949, 1954-58 Miss J. D. Corwin, 1946-48 Richmond K. Anderson, 1948-54 LeRoy R. Allen, 1958-67 Division Directors in New York Richard M. Pearce (Medical Sciences), 1929-30 Alan Gregg (Medical Sciences), 1931-50 George K. Strode (Medicine and Public Health), 1951 Andrew J. Warren (Medicine and Public Health), 1951-54 John C. Bugher (Medical Education and Public Health), 1955-59 Robert S. Morison (Biological and Medical Research), 1955-59; (Medical and Natural Sciences), 1964-70 John M. Weir (Medical and Natural Sciences), 1964-70
  Indian Agricultural Program
  Field Directors in New Delhi Ralph W. Cummings, 1957-66 Guy B. Baird, 1967-71 Ordway Starnes, 1971-73 Wayne H. Freeman, 1974-75
  Division Directors in New York Warren Weaver (Natural Sciences and Agriculture), 1951-55 J. George Harrar (Agricultural Sciences), 1955-59 Albert H. Moseman (Agricultural Sciences), 1960-65 Sterling Wortman (Agricultural Sciences), 1966-70 John A. Pino (Agricultural Sciences), 1970-82
  Humanities and Social Sciences Program
  Foundation Representative in New Delhi Chadbourne Gilpatric (Humanities and Social Sciences), 1964-72
  Division Directors in New York Kenneth W. Thompson, acting (Humanities and Social Sciences), 1962-64 Joseph E. Black (Humanities and Social Sciences), 1964-70 Norman Lloyd (Arts and Humanities), 1970-73
  For information about specific grants to individuals or institutions in India, researchers should consult the grant files (1913-73) for India, located in Record Groups 1.1 and 1.2 (Projects), Series 464 (India), in the Rockefeller Foundation Archives.
  RELATED MATERIALS
  The following Record Groups in the Rockefeller Foundation Archives at the Rockefeller Archive Center contain material bearing upon the Foundation's work in India:
  RG 1.1: Projects RG 1.2: Projects RG 2: General Correspondence RG 3: Administration, Program, and Policy RG 5: International Health Board RG 6.13: Mexico Field Office RG 12.1: Officers' Diaries RG 12.2: Officers' Diaries RG 12.3: Officers' Diaries RG 13: Oral Histories, RF Field Officers (open by permission of (the Secretary of the Rockefeller Foundation)
  Annual reports of the Rockefeller Foundation Confidential Monthly Report, for the Information of the Trustees
  PHOTOGRAPHS
  Four folders of photographs were removed from Record Group 6.7 during processing and added to the Photograph Collection of the Archive Center. These photographs are filed by country number, 464 India, and thereunder alphabetically by subject. They are interfiled with other photographs of India taken from Record Group 1.1 and 1.2 (Projects). Included are photographs of CIMMYT work in Mexico (n.d.), agricultural scenes in India (1958-59), compartment cages used for rearing the sorghum shoot fly (1971), and a disbound scrapbook of captioned photographs (1957) showing investigations into the virus known as Kyasanoor Forest Disease.
  - Indian Agricultural Program - General Administrative Files, ca. 1952-1976; I1; 21 __Boxes __6.6 cubic feet
    Subgroup I, Series 1, General Administrative Files (1952-1976), contains correspondence and miscellaneous materials pertaining to general field office operations. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by subject. Filed under "Government of India" are copies of agreements and understandings (1957-1976) reached between the RF and the Indian government. The bulk of the Government of India correspondence consists of letters between the field office, government ministries, and New York headquarters concerning Indian government procedures for proposing and clearing grants to agencies or institutions in India. It also covers procedures for reporting renewals, extensions, or amendments of fellowships; sending dollar checks to the United States; and preparing income tax reports. Additional correspondence concerns budgetary matters, field office bank accounts, employee housing, and staffing of the American International School, where RF staff enrolled their children.
    Other material in Series 1 is filed under the heading "Operating Records" and fills boxes 7-21. Operating records include customs clearance permits, leases for rented offices and apartments in New Delhi, personnel policy files, record-keeping procedures, and inventories of imported field equipment.
    Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Correspondence - Accounting/Auditing, 1961-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - American International School, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 0001a)
    - Correspondence - American International School, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 0001b)
    - Correspondence - American International School, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 0001c)
    - Correspondence - Banks - First National City Bank, New Delhi, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence - Banks - State Bank of Hyderabad, 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence - Banks - Syndicate Bank, New Delhi, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence - Comptroller's Office, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence - Government of India - Agreements and Understandings, 1957-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence - Government of India - Income Tax - RF Staff, 1953-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence - Government of India - Income Tax - Alexander & Company, Consultants, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence - Government of India - Income Tax - Alexander & Company, Consultants, 1955-1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence - Government of India - Income Tax - New York Office, 1953-1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      See also Box 4, Folder 26.
    - Correspondence - Government of India - RF Responses to Parliament Questions, 1954-1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence - Government of India - Policy and Procedure - General, 1958-1963, 1966-1967, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence - Government of India - Policy and Procedure - Publication of Maps of India, 1965-1967, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, January-October 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, June-October 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Foreign Colleagues, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Foreign Colleagues, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Foreign Colleagues, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Housing, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Income Tax, 1957-1975 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      See also Box 2, Folder 10.
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - New York Office, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Requests for Information, 1967-1973 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Visit of President John Knowles, June 1973 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Visitors to India, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Historical Data on RF Assistance to India, 1953-1970, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Historical Data on RF Assistance to India, 1953-1970, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Historical Data on RF Assistance to India, 1953-1970, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Historical Data on RF Assistance to India, 1953-1970, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Historical Notes on RF Assistance to India, 1952-1966 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Historical Notes on RF Assistance to India, 1952-1966 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Memoranda - Internal, 1958-1972 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Memoranda - Internal, 1958-1972 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Memoranda - Internal, 1958-1972 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Memoranda - Received from New York Office, 1959-1973 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Memoranda - Received from New York Office, 1959-1973 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Memoranda - Received from New York Office, 1959-1973 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance Permits, 1962-1974 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance Permits, 1962-1974 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 55)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 56)
    - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - Operating Records - Guest Lists, 1969-1973 (Box 9, Folder 58)
    - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - RF Offices - General, 1958-1974 (Box 9, Folder 59)
    - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - RF Offices - General, 1958-1974 (Box 9, Folder 60)
    - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - 6 Dharma Marg, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 61)
    - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - Hyderabad Apartment, 1969-1971 (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - 18 Kautilya Marg, 1961-1965 (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - 27 Malcha Marg, 1968-1971 (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - 82D Malcha Marg, 1961-1971 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - 158 Malcha Marg, 1961-1968 (Box 9, Folder 66)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Central Government Health Scheme, 1965-1973 (Box 10, Folder 67)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Central Government Health Scheme, 1965-1973 (Box 10, Folder 68)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Central Government Health Scheme, 1965-1973 (Box 10, Folder 69)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Central Government Health Scheme, 1965-1973 (Box 10, Folder 70)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Central Government Health Scheme - Monthly Statements, 1965-1973 (Box 10, Folder 71)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Delhi Medical and Nursing Home Benefits Scheme, 1959-1964 (Box 10, Folder 72)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Delhi Medical and Nursing Home Benefits Scheme, 1959-1964 (Box 10, Folder 73)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Health Care Program, 1960-1973 (Box 11, Folder 74)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Health Care Program, 1960-1973 (Box 11, Folder 75)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Leave Policy, 1958-1968 (Box 11, Folder 76)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Perquisites, 1959-1973 (Box 11, Folder 77)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Retirement Security Fund, 1953-1972 (Box 11, Folder 78)
    - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Retirement Security Fund, 1953-1972 (Box 11, Folder 79)
    - Operating Records - Record-Keeping and Filing Procedures, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 80)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Inventory - General, 1957-1972 (Box 11, Folder 81)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Inventory of Field Equipment - Manuscript, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 82)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Inventory of Field Equipment - 5 x 7 Cards, 1957-1974 (Box 12, Folder 83)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Inventory of Field Equipment - 5 x 7 Cards, 1957-1974 (Box 13, Folder 84)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Inventory of Field Equipment - 5 x 7 Cards, 1957-1974 (Box 14, Folder 85)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Inventory of Field Equipment - 5 x 7 Cards, 1957-1974 (Box 15, Folder 86)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Inventory of Field Equipment - 5 x 7 Cards, 1957-1974 (Box 16, Folder 87)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Inventory of Field Equipment - 5 x 7 Cards, 1957-1974 (Box 17, Folder 88)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Inventory of Field Equipment - 5 x 7 Cards, 1957-1974 (Box 18, Folder 89)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Inventory of Field Equipment - 5 x 7 Cards, 1957-1974 (Box 19, Folder 90)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Lists of Equipment Supplied, 1957-1972 (Box 20, Folder 91)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Lists of Equipment Supplied, 1957-1972 (Box 20, Folder 92)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Lists of Equipment Supplied, 1957-1972 (Box 20, Folder 93)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Lists of Equipment Supplied, 1957-1972 (Box 20, Folder 94)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Lists of Equipment Supplied, 1957-1972 (Box 20, Folder 95)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Lists of Equipment Supplied, 1957-1972 (Box 20, Folder 96)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Lists of Equipment Supplied, 1957-1972 (Box 20, Folder 97)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Master List of Equipment Supplied, 1971-1974 (Box 20, Folder 98)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Master List of Equipment Supplied, 1971-1974 (Box 20, Folder 99)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Master List of Equipment Supplied, 1971-1974 (Box 21, Folder 100)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Master List of Equipment Supplied, 1971-1974 (Box 21, Folder 101)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Receipts - Equipment Sales, 1973 (Box 21, Folder 102)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Transfer of Title, Donation of Equipment, 1970-1973 (Box 21, Folder 103)
    - Operating Records - Supplies and Equipment - Transfer of Title, Donation of Equipment, 1970-1973 (Box 21, Folder 104)
  - Indian Agricultural Program - Administrative Files, 1950-1975, n.d.; I2; 12 __Boxes __4.8 cubic feet
    Subgroup I, Series 2, IAP Administrative Files, includes correspondence, minutes, program development files, and fellowship and scholarship files (1950-1975) relating to the planning and review of the IAP research programs and to international programs with which the Foundation collaborated.
    Field office correspondence with New York headquarters, the Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR), and the Ministry of Food and Agricultural fills boxes 22 through 25. Correspondence with the New York office relates to travel, staffing needs, funding, equipment and supplies, and seed shipments. Letters between IAP field directors and the Directors General of the ICAR, Dr. B. P. Pal and Dr. A. B. Joshi, pertain to meetings and workshops, crop programs, research evaluations and publications.
    Correspondence with representatives of international organizations and agencies is arranged alphabetically by country or name of organization and fills boxes 29 through 33. Letters concern agriculture assistance programs undertaken by other organizations, as well as preparations for IAP staff visits to countries outside India. As a whole, the correspondence reveals the international network of technical know-how brought to bear upon improving Asian agriculture between 1958 and 1973.
    The program development files in Series 2 contain influential reports on RF agricultural policy and Indian agriculture. These include a statement by RF Director Warren Weaver, "The Program in the Natural Sciences," prepared in 1950, one year before the creation of the Natural Sciences and Agriculture Division. Also present is a 1951 memorandum from Weaver to Dr. Richmond K. Anderson, the RF Representative in India, in which Weaver outlines procedures for referring to New York Indian requests for information on agricultural grants. Also of interest is the 1952 report, "Notes on Indian Agriculture," by J. G. Harrar, Paul C. Mangelsdorf, and Warren Weaver. This report led to several follow-up visits by RF representatives and ultimately to India's request for a collaborative agricultural program.
    Records are arranged alphabetically by type of material from "Correspondence" through "Program development files." These files are followed by International Development Programs, International Organizations, and United States Agencies.
    Correspondence with representatives of international organizations and agencies is arranged alphabetically by country or name of organization.